<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj "&#8288;">
]>

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" submissionType="IETF"
category="std" ipr="trust200902" consensus="true"
docName="draft-ietf-avtcore-rtp-j2k-scl-01" xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Sub-codestream latency J2K over RTP">RTP Payload Format for
    sub-codestream latency JPEG 2000 streaming</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-avtcore-rtp-j2k-scl-01"/>

    <author initials='P.-A.' surname='Lemieux' fullname='Pierre-Anthony Lemieux' role="editor">

      <organization>Sandflow Consulting LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>San Mateo</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pal@sandflow.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='D. S.' surname='Taubman' fullname='David Scott Taubman'>
      <organization abbrev="University of New South Wales">University of New
      South Wales</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Sydney</city>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>
        <email>d.taubman@unsw.edu.au</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <area>Applications and Real-Time Area</area>
    <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Core Maintenance</workgroup>

    <keyword>JPEG 2000</keyword>
    <keyword>J2K</keyword>
    <keyword>HTJ2K</keyword>
    <keyword>low latency</keyword>
    <keyword>scalable</keyword>
    <keyword>streaming</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This RTP payload format defines the streaming of a video signal encoded
      as a sequence of JPEG 2000 codestreams. The format allows sub-codestream
      latency, such that the first RTP packet for a given codestream can be
      emitted before the entire codestream is available.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This RTP payload format specifies the streaming of a video signal
      encoded as a sequence of JPEG 2000 codestreams.</t>

      <t>In addition to supporting a variety of frame scanning techniques
      (progressive, interlaced and progressive segmented frame) and image
      characteristics, the payload format includes the following features
      specifically designed for streaming applications:</t>

      <ul>
        <li>the payload format allows sub-codestream latency such that the first
        RTP packet of a given codestream to be emitted before the entire
        codestream is available. Specifically, the payload format does not rely
        on the JPEG 2000 PLM and PLT marker segments for recovery after RTP
        Packet loss since these markers can only be written after the codestream
        is complete and are thus incompatible with sub-codestream latency.
        Instead, the payload format includes payload header fields
        (<tt>ORDH</tt>, <tt>ORDB</tt>, <tt>POS</tt> and <tt>PID</tt>) that
        indicates whether the RTP packet contains a resynchronization (resync)
        point and how a recipient can restart codestream processing from that
        resync point. This contrasts with <xref target="RFC5371"/>, which also
        specifies an RTP payload format for JPEG 2000, but relies on codestream
        structures that cannot be emitted until the entire codestream is
        available.</li>

        <li>as in <xref target="RFC4175"/>, the payload header contains an
        extension (<tt>ESEQ</tt>) to the standard 16-bit RTP sequence number,
        enabling the payload format to accommodate high data rates without
        ambiguity. This is necessary as the standard sequence number will roll
        over very quickly for high data rates likely to be encountered in this
        application. For example, the standard sequence number will roll over in
        0.5 seconds with a 1-Gbps video stream with RTP Packet sizes of at least
        1000 octets, which can be a problem for detecting loss and out-of-order
        packets particularly in instances where the round-trip time is greater
        than the roll over period (0.5 seconds in this example).</li>

        <li>the payload header optionally contains a temporal offset
        (<tt>PTSTAMP</tt>) relative to the first RTP Packet with the same value
        of RTP <tt>timestamp</tt> field (<xref target="def-timestamp"/>). The
        higher resolution of <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> compared to the <tt>timestamp</tt>
        allows receivers to recover the sender's clock more rapidly.</li>
      </ul>

      <t>Finally, the payload format also makes use of the unique scalability
      features of JPEG 2000 to allow a network agent or recipient to discard
      resolutions and/or quality layers merely by inspecting payload headers
      (<tt>QUAL</tt> and <tt>RES</tt> fields), without having to parse the
      underlying codestream.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Requirements Language</name>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
      they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Media format description</name>
      <t>The following summarizes the structure of the JPEG 2000 codestream,
      which is specified in detail at <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>.</t>

      <t>NOTE: as described at <xref target="sec-codestream"/>, a JPEG 2000
      codestream allows capabilities defined in any part of the JPEG 2000 family
      of standards, including those specified in <xref target="jpeg2000-2"/> and
      <xref target="jpeg2000-15"/>.</t>

      <t>JPEG 2000 represents an image as one or more components, e.g., R, G and
      B, each uniformly sampled on a common rectangular reference grid. An image
      can be further divided into contiguous rectangular tiles that are each
      independently coded and decoded.</t>

      <t>NOTE: This payload format allows the transmission of  multi-tile images
      as multiple single-tile images per stream, as specified at <xref
      target="sec-mt-images"/>.</t>

      <t>JPEG 2000 codes each image as a standalone codestream. Each codestream
      consists of (i) marker segments, which contain coding parameters and
      metadata, and (ii) coded data.</t>

      <t>The codestream starts with an SOC marker segment and ends with an EOC
      marker segment. The main header of the codestream consists of marker
      segments between the SOC and first SOT marker segment and contains
      information that applies to the codestream in its entirety. It is
      generally impossible to decode a codestream without its main header.</t>

      <t>The rest of the codestream consists of additional marker segments
      (tile-part headers) interleaved with coded image data.</t>

      <t>The coded image data ultimately consists of code-blocks, each
      containing coded samples belonging to a rectangular (spatial) region
      within one resolution level of one component. Code-blocks are further
      collected into precincts, which, accordingly, represents code-blocks
      belonging to a spatial region within one resolution level of one
      component.</t>

      <t>The image coded data can be arranged into several progression orders,
      which dictates which aspect of the image appears first in the codestream
      (in terms of byte offset). The progression orders are parameterized
      according to:</t>

      <dl>
        <dt>Position (P)</dt>
        <dd>The first lines of the image come before the last lines of the
        image.</dd>
        <dt>Component (C)</dt>
        <dd>The first component of the image come before the last component of
        the image.</dd>
        <dt>Resolution Layer (R)</dt>
        <dd>The information needed to reconstruct the lower spatial resolutions
        of the image come before the information needed to reconstruct the
        higher spatial resolutions of the image.</dd>
        <dt>Quality Layer (L)</dt>
        <dd>The information needed to reconstruct the most-significant bits of
        each sample come before the information needed to reconstruct the
        least-significant bit of each sample.</dd>
      </dl>

      <t>For example, in the PRCL progression order, the information needed to
      reconstruct the first lines of the image come before that needed to
      reconstruct the last lines of the image and, within a collection of lines,
      the information needed to reconstruct the lower spatial resolutions of the
      image come before the information needed to reconstruct the higher spatial
      resolutions. This progression order is particular useful for sub-frame
      latency operations.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Video signal description</name>
      <t>This RTP payload format supports three distinct video frame scanning
      techniques:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>Progressive frame</li>
        <li>Interlaced frame, where each frame consists of two fields. Field 1
        occurs temporarily before Field 2. The height in lines of each field is
        half the height of the image.</li>
        <li>Progressive segmented frame (PsF), where each frame consists of two
        segments. Segment 1 contains the odd lines (1, 3, 5, 7,...) of a frame
        and Segment 2 contains the even lines (2, 4, 6, 8,...) of the same
        frame, where lines from the top of the frame to the bottom of the frame
        are numbered sequentially starting at 1.</li>
      </ul>
      <t>All frames are scanned left to right, top to bottom.</t>
    </section>

    <section>
      <name>Payload Format</name>
      <section>
        <name>General</name>

        <figure anchor="fig-payload-header">
          <name>Packetization of a sequence of JPEG 2000 codestreams (not to
          scale). P are arbitrary padding bytes.</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art">
<![CDATA[
        <----------- Codestream (image) --------->
        |                                        |
        < Extended Header >                      |
        |                 |                      |
        +-----+-----+-----+------------//--+-----+-----+---------
        | SOC | ... | SOD | .............. | EOC |  P  | SOC  ...
        +-----+-----+-----+------------//--+-----+-----+---------
        |                                              |
        |                                              |
        |                                              |
        +---------------------+------+-//--+-----------+---------
Packets |        Main         | Body | ... |    Body   | Main ...
        +---------------------+------+-//--+-----------+---------
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Each RTP packet, as specified at <xref target="RFC3550"/>, is either
        a Main Packet or a Body Packet.</t>

        <t>A Main Packet consists of the following ordered sequence of
        structures concatenated without gaps:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>the RTP Fixed Header;</li>
          <li>a Main Packet Payload Header, as specified at <xref
          target="sec-main-packet-header"/>; and</li>
          <li>the payload, which consists of a JPEG 2000 codestream
          fragment.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>A Body Packet consists of the following ordered sequence of
          structures concatenated without gaps:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>the RTP Fixed Header;</li>
          <li>a Body Packet Payload Header, as specified at <xref
          target="sec-body-packet-header"/>; and</li>
          <li>the payload, which consists of a JPEG 2000 codestream
          fragment.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>When concatenated, the sequence of JPEG 2000 codestream fragments
        emitted by the sender MUST be a sequence of JPEG 2000 codestreams where
        two successive JPEG 2000 codestreams MAY be separated by one or more
        arbitrary padding bytes (see <xref target="fig-payload-header"/>).</t>

        <t>The JPEG 2000 codestreams MUST conform to <xref
        target="sec-codestream"/>.</t>

        <t>The padding bytes MUST be ignored by the recipient.</t>

        <t>NOTE: Padding bytes can be used to achieve constant bit rate
        transmission.</t>

        <t> A JPEG 2000 codestream consists of the bytes between, and including,
        the SOC and EOC markers, as defined in <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>.</t>

        <t>A JPEG 2000 codestream fragment does not necessarily contain complete
        JPEG 2000 packets, as defined in <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>.</t>

        <t>A JPEG 2000 codestream Extended Header consists of the bytes between,
        and including, the SOC marker and the first SOD marker.</t>

        <t>The payload of a Body Packet MUST NOT contain any bytes of the JPEG
        2000 codestream Extended Header.</t>

        <t>The payload of a Main Packet MUST contain at least one byte of the
        JPEG 2000 codestream Extended Header and MAY contain bytes other than
        those of the JPEG 2000 codestream Extended Header.</t>

        <t>A payload MUST NOT contain bytes from more than one JPEG 2000
        codestream.</t>

      </section>

      <section>
        <name>RTP Fixed Header Usage</name>

        <t>The following RTP header fields have a specific meaning in the
        context of this payload format:</t>

        <dl newline="true">
          <dt><tt>marker</tt></dt>
          <dd>
            <dl>
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>The payload contains an EOC marker.</dd>

              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>Otherwise</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-timestamp"><tt>timestamp</tt></dt>
          <dd>
            <t>The <tt>timestamp</tt> is the presentation time of the image to
            which the payload belongs.</t>

            <t>The <tt>timestamp</tt> clock rate is 90 kHz.</t>

            <t>The <tt>timestamp</tt> of successive progressive frames MUST
            advance at regular increments based on the instantaneous video frame
            rate.</t>

            <t>The <tt>timestamp</tt> of Field 1 of successive interlaced frames
            MUST advance at regular increments based on the instantaneous video
            frame rate, and the <tt>Timestamp</tt> of Field 2 MUST be offset
            from the <tt>timestamp</tt> of Field 1 by one half of the
            instantaneous frame period.</t>

            <t>The <tt>timestamp</tt> of both segments of a progressive
            segmented frame MUST be equal.</t>

            <t><tt>timestamp</tt> of all RTP packets of a given image MUST be
            equal.</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-seq"><tt>sequence number</tt></dt>
          <dd>
          <t>The low-order bits of the RTP sequence number.</t>

          <t>The higher order bits of the RTP sequence number are contained in
          the <tt>ESEQ</tt> field, which is specified at <xref
          target="def-ESEQ"/>.</t>

          <t>The RTP sequence number is calculated as follows:</t>
          <t><tt>ESEQ * 65536 + sequence number</tt></t></dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-main-packet-header">
        <name>Main Packet Payload Header</name>
        <t><xref target="fig-main-payload-header"/> specifies the structure of the
        payload header. Fields are interpreted as unsigned binary integers in
        network order.</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-main-payload-header">
          <name>Structure of the Main Packet Payload Header</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art">
<![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|MH | TP  |ORDH |P|XTRAC|        PTSTAMP        |     ESEQ      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|R|S|C| RSVD  |*|    PRIMS      |    TRANS      |      MAT      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                              XTRAB                            |
|                               ...                             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

* RANGE
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <dl newline="true">
          <dt anchor="def-MH">MH (Codestream Main Header Presence)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>The RTP Packet is a Body Packet.</dd>
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>The RTP Packet is a Main Packet and the codestream has more
              than one Main Packet. The next RTP Packet is a Main Packet.</dd>
              <dt>2</dt>
              <dd>The RTP Packet is a Main Packet and the codestream has more
              than one Main Packet. The next RTP Packet is a Body Packet.</dd>
              <dt>3</dt>
              <dd>The RTP Packet is a Main Packet and the codestream has exactly
              one Main Packet.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-TP">TP (Image Type)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>Indicates the scanning structure of the image to which the
            payload belongs.</t>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>Progressive frame.</dd>

              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>Field 1 of an interlaced frame, where the first line of the
              field is the first line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>2</dt>
              <dd>Field 2 of an interlaced frame, where the first line of the
              field is the second line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>3</dt>
              <dd>Field 1 of an interlaced frame, where the first line of the
              field is the second line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>4</dt>
              <dd>Field 2 of an interlaced frame, where the first line of the
              field is the first line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>5</dt>
              <dd>Segment 1 of a progressive segmented frame, where the
              first line of the image is the first line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>6</dt>
              <dd>Segment 2 of a progressive segmented frame, where the
              first line of the image is the second line of the frame.</dd>

              <dt>7</dt>
              <dd>Extension value. See <xref target="sec-receiver-ext"/> and
              <xref target="sec-sender-ext"/>.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-ORDH">ORDH (Progression Order [Main Packet])</dt>
          <dd>
              <t>Specifies the progression order used by the codestream and
              whether resync points are signaled.</t>
              <dl newline="true">
                <dt>0</dt>
                <dd>Resync points are not necessarily signaled. The progression
                order can vary over the codestream.</dd>

                <dt>1</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is LRCP for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>2</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is RLCP for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>3</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is RPCL for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>4</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is PCRL for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>5</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is CPRL for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>6</dt>
                <dd>The progression order is PRCL for the entire codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>

                <dt>7</dt>
                <dd>The progression order can vary over the codestream. The
                first resync point is specified in every Body Packet that
                contains one or more resync points.</dd>
              </dl>

              <t><tt>ORDH</tt> MUST be 0 is the codestream consists of more than
              one tile.</t>

              <t>NOTE: Only <tt>ORDH</tt> = 4 and <tt>ORDH</tt> = 6 allow
              sub-codestream latency streaming.</t>

              <t>NOTE: Progression order PRCL is defined in <xref
              target="jpeg2000-2"/>. The other progression orders are specified
              in <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>.</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-P">P (Precision Timestamp Presence)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd><tt>PTSTAMP</tt> is not used.</dd>
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd><tt>PTSTAMP</tt> is used.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-XTRAC">XTRAC (Extension Payload Length)</dt>
          <dd>Length, in multiples of 4 bytes, of the <tt>XTRAB</tt> field.</dd>

          <dt anchor="def-PTSTAMP">PTSTAMP (Precision Timestamp)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>PTSTAMP = (<tt>timestamp</tt> + <tt>TOFF</tt>) mod 4096, if
            <tt>P</tt> = 1 in the Main Packet of this codestream.</t>

            <t><tt>TOFF</tt> is the transmission time of this RTP Packet, in the
            timebase of the <tt>timestamp</tt> clock and relative to the first
            packet with the same <tt>timestamp</tt> value.</t>

            <t><tt>TOFF</tt> = 0 in the first RTP Packet with the same
            <tt>timestamp</tt> value.</t>

            <t><tt>PTSTAMP</tt> = 0, if <tt>P</tt> = 0 in the Main Packet of this
            codestream.</t>

            <t>NOTE: As described at <xref target="sec-sender-ptstamp"/> and
            <xref target="sec-recv-ptstamp"/>, <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> is intended to
            improve clock recovery at the receiver and only applies when the
            transmission time of two consecutive RTP packets with identical
            <tt>timestamp</tt> fields differ by no more than 45 ms =
            4095/90,000. <xref target="RFC5450"/> provides addresses the general
            case when a RTP packet is transmitted at a time other than its
            nominal transmission time.</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-ESEQ">ESEQ (Extended Sequence Number)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>The high order bits of the RTP sequence number.</t>
            <t><xref target="def-seq"/> specifies the The low-order bits of the
            RTP sequence number and the formula to compute the RTP sequence
            number</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-R">R (Codestream Main Header Reuse)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>Determines whether Main Packet and codestream header information
            can be reused across codestreams.</t>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>All Main Packets in this stream, as identified by its
                <tt>SSRC</tt> value:</t>
                <ul>
                  <li>MUST have identical Main Packet Payload Headers, with the
                  exception of their <tt>TP</tt>, <tt>MH</tt>, <tt>ESEQ</tt> and
                  <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> fields;</li>
                  <li>MUST contain the same codestream main header information,
                  with the exception of the SOT and COM marker segments, and any
                  pointer marker segments; and</li>
                  <li>MUST NOT contain bytes other than Extended Header
                  bytes.</li>
                </ul>
              </dd>
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>Otherwise</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-S">S (Parameterized Colorspace Presence)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd><t>Component colorimetry is not specified, and left to the
              session or the application.</t>
              <t><tt>PRIMS</tt>, <tt>TRANS</tt> and <tt>MAT</tt> and
              <tt>RANGE</tt>
              MUST be zero.</t>
            </dd>
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Component colorimetry is specified by the <tt>PRIMS</tt>,
                TRANS and <tt>MAT</tt> and <tt>RANGE</tt> fields.</t>
                <t>The codestream components MUST conform to one of the
                combinations at <xref target="t-color-map"/>.</t>
                <table anchor="t-color-map">
                  <name>Mapping of codestream components to color
                  channels</name>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th rowspan="2">Combination name</th>
                      <th colspan="4">Component index</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>0</th>
                      <th>1</th>
                      <th>2</th>
                      <th>3</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <th>Y</th><td>Y</td><td></td><td></td><td></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>YA</th><td>Y</td><td>A</td><td></td><td></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>RGB</th><td>R</td><td>G</td><td>B</td><td></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>RGBA</th><td>R</td><td>G</td><td>B</td><td>A</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>YCbCr</th><td>Y</td><td>C<sub>B</sub></td>
                      <td>C<sub>R</sub></td><td></td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th>YCbCrA</th><td>Y</td><td>C<sub>B</sub></td>
                      <td>C<sub>R</sub></td><td>A</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                  <tfoot>
                    <tr>
                      <td colspan="5">The channel <tt>A</tt> is an opacity
                      channel. The minimum sample value (0) indicates a
                      completely transparent sample, and the maximum sample
                      value (as determined by the bit depth of the codestream
                      component) indicates a completely opaque sample. The
                      opacity channel MUST map to a component with unsigned
                      samples.</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tfoot>
                </table>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-C">C (Code-block Caching Usage)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>Code-block caching is not in use.</dd>
              <dt>1</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Code-block caching is in use.</t>
                <t><tt>R</tt> MUST be equal to 1.</t>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-RSVD">RSVD (Reserved)</dt>
          <dd>Reserved value. See <xref target="sec-receiver-reserved"/> and
          <xref target="sec-sender-reserved"/>.</dd>

          <dt anchor="def-F">RANGE (Video Full Range Usage)</dt>
          <dd>Value of the VideoFullRangeFlag specified in <xref
          target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></dd>

          <dt anchor="def-PRIMS">PRIMS (Color Primaries)</dt>
          <dd>One of the ColourPrimaries values specified in <xref
          target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></dd>

          <dt anchor="def-TRANS">TRANS (Transfer Characteristics)</dt>
          <dd>One of the TransferCharacteristics values specified in
          <xref target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></dd>

          <dt anchor="def-MAT"><tt>MAT (Color Matrix Coefficients)</tt></dt>
          <dd>One of the MatrixCoefficients values specified in <xref
          target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></dd>

          <dt anchor="def-XTRAB">XTRAB (Extension Payload)</dt>
          <dd>Allows the contents of the Main Packet Payload Header to be
          extended in the future. See <xref target="sec-receiver-xtrab"/> and
          <xref target="sec-sender-xtrab"/>.</dd>

        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-body-packet-header">
        <name>Body Packet Payload Header</name>
        <t><xref target="fig-body-payload-header"/> specifies the structure of
        the Body Packet Payload Header. Fields are interpreted as unsigned
        binary integers in network order.</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-body-payload-header">
          <name>Structure of the Body Packet Payload Header</name>
          <artwork type="ascii-art">
<![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|MH | TP  |RES  |*|QUAL |       PTSTAMP         |     ESEQ      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         POS           |                  PID                  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

* ORDH
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <dl newline="true">
          <dt anchor="def-RES">RES (Resolution Layers)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>The payload can contribute to all resolution layers.</dd>

              <dt>Otherwise</dt>
              <dd>The payload contains at least one byte of one JPEG 2000 packet
              belonging to resolution level (N<sub>L</sub> + RES - 7) but does
              not contain any byte of any JPEG 2000 packet belonging to lower
              resolution levels. N<sub>L</sub> is the number of decomposition
              levels of the codestream.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-ORDB">ORDB (Progression Order [Body Packet]</dt>
          <dd>
              <dl newline="true">
                <dt>0</dt>
                <dd>No resync point is specified for the payload.</dd>

                <dt>1</dt>
                <dd>The payload contains a resync point.</dd>
              </dl>
              <t><tt>ORDB</tt> MUST be 0 is the codestream consists of more than
              one tile.</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-QUAL">QUAL (Quality Layers)</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt>0</dt>
              <dd>The payload can contribute to all quality layers.</dd>

              <dt>Otherwise</dt>
              <dd>The payload contributes only to quality layer index
              <tt>QUAL</tt> or above.</dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-POS">POS (Resync Point Offset)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>Byte offset from the start of the payload to the first byte of
            the resync point belonging to the precinct identified by PID.</t>
            <t><tt>POS</tt> MUST be 0 if <tt>ORDB</tt> = 0.</t>
          </dd>

          <dt anchor="def-PID">PID (Precinct Identifier)</dt>
          <dd>
            <t>Unique identifier of the precinct of the resync point.</t>

            <t><tt>PID = c + s * num_components</tt></t>

            <t>where:</t>
            <ul>
              <li><em>c</em> is the index (starting from 0) of the image
              component to which the precinct belongs;</li>
              <li><em>s</em> is a sequence number which identifies the precinct
              within its tile-component; and</li>
              <li><em>num_components</em> is the number of components of the
              codestream.</li>
            </ul>

            <t>If <tt>PID</tt> is present, the payload MUST NOT contain
            codestream bytes from more than one precinct.</t>

            <t><tt>PID</tt> MUST be 0 if <tt>ORDB</tt> = 0.</t>

            <t>NOTE: <tt>PID</tt> is identical to precinct identifier I
            specified in <xref target="jpeg2000-9"/>.</t>
          </dd>

        </dl>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-codestream">
      <name>JPEG 2000 codestream requirements</name>
      <section>
        <name>General</name>
        <t>The JPEG 2000 codestream MAY include capabilities beyond those
        specified at <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>, including those specified in
        <xref target="jpeg2000-2"/> and <xref target="jpeg2000-15"/>.</t>

        <t>NOTE: The <tt>Rsiz</tt> parameter and <tt>CAP</tt> marker segments of
        each JPEG 2000 codestream contain detailed information on the
        capabilities necessary to decode the codestream.</t>

        <t>NOTE: The <tt>caps</tt> media type parameter defined in
        <xref target="sec-media-type-def"/> allows applications to signal
        required device capabilities.</t>

        <t>NOTE: The block coder specified at <xref target="jpeg2000-15"/>
        improves throughput and reduces latency compared to the original
        arithmetic block coder defined in <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>.</t>

        <t>For interlaced or progressive segmented frames, the height specified
        in the JPEG 2000 main header MUST be the height in lines of the field or
        the segment, respectively.</t>

        <t>If any decomposition level involves only horizontal decomposition
        then no decomposition level MUST involve only vertical decomposition;
        and conversely, if any decomposition level involves only vertical
        decomposition then no decomposition level MUST involve only horizontal
        decomposition.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-mt-images">
        <name>Transmitting multi-tile images as multiple single-tile images</name>

        <t>A sequence of multi-tile images can be transmitted by splitting it
        into multiple sequences of single-tile images, where:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>each sequence of single-tile images corresponds to a unique tile
          of the multi-tile image;</li>
          <li>each sequence of single-tile images is transmitted in a separate
          RTP stream;</li>
          <li>the coordinates of each single-tile image are expressed using the
          coordinate system of the multi-tile image; and</li>
          <li>the bitstreams of each of each single-tile image are identical to
          the corresponding bitstreams in the multi-tile image.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>Such sequences of single-tile images are identified using the
        <tt>tile</tt> media type parameter specified at <xref
        target="dt-tile"/>.</t>

      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="sec-sender">
      <name>Sender requirements</name>

      <section>
        <name>Main Packet</name>

        <t>Only Main Packets MAY contain bytes of the JPEG 2000 codestream
        Extended Header.</t>

        <t>The sender MUST either emit a single Main Packet with <tt>MH</tt> =
        3, or one or more Main Packets with <tt>MH</tt> = 1 followed by a
        single Main Packet with <tt>MH</tt> = 2.</t>

        <t>The Main Packet Payload Headers fields MUST be identical in all Main
        Packet of a given codestream, with the exception of:</t>
        <ul>
          <li><tt>MH</tt>;</li>
          <li><tt>ESEQ</tt>; and</li>
          <li><tt>PTSTAMP</tt>.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>RTP Packet filtering</name>
        <t>A network agent MAY strip out RTP Packet from a codestream that are
        of no interest to a particular client, e.g., based on a resolution or a
        spatial region of interest. Such a network agent SHOULD include a CSRC
        identifier to identify the SSRC field of the original source from which
        content was stripped.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>Resync point</name>
        <t>A resync point is the first byte of JPEG 2000 packet header data for
        a precinct and for which PID &lt; 2<sup>24</sup>.</t>

        <t>NOTE: Resync points cannot be specified if the codestream consists of
        more than one tile (<tt>ORDB</tt> and <tt>ORDH</tt> are both equal to
        zero). To transmit codestreams that consist of more than one tile and
        benefit from resync points, the technique specified at <xref
        target="sec-mt-images"/> can be used.</t>

        <t>NOTE: A resync point can be used by a receiver to process a
        codestream even if earlier packets in the codestream have been
        corrupted, lost or deliberately discarded by a network agent. As a
        corollary, resync points can be used by a network agent to discard
        packets that are not relevant to a given rendering resolution or region
        of interest. Resync points play a role similar to pointer marker
        segments, albeit tailored for high bandwidth low latency streaming
        applications.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-sender-ptstamp">
        <name>PTSTAMP field</name>

        <t>A sender SHOULD set <tt>P</tt> = 1, but only if it can generate
        <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> accurately.</t>

        <t><tt>PTSTAMP</tt> can be derived from the same clock that is used to
        produce the 32-bit <tt>timestamp</tt> field in the RTP fixed header.
        Specifically, a sender maintains, at least conceptually, a 32-bit
        counter that is incremented by a 90kHz clock. The counter is sampled at
        the point when each RTP Packet is or SHOULD be at least notionally
        transmitted and the 12 LSBs of the sample are stored in the
        <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> field.</t>

        <t>If <tt>P</tt> = 1, then the transmission time <tt>TOFF</tt> (as
        defined at <xref target="def-PTSTAMP"></xref>) for two consecutive RTP
        packets with identical <tt>timestamp</tt> fields MUST NOT differ by more
        than 4095.</t>
      </section>

      <section>
        <name>RES field</name>
        <t>A sender SHOULD set <tt>RES</tt> &gt; 0 whenever possible.</t>

        <t>NOTE: While a sender can always safely set <tt>RES</tt> = 0, this
        makes it more difficult to discard packets based on resolution, as
        described at <xref target="recv-RES"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-sender-xtrab">
        <name>Extra information</name>
        <t>The sender MUST set the value of <tt>XTRAC</tt> to 0.</t>

        <t>Future edition of this specification can permit other values.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-sender-reserved">
        <name>Reserved values</name>
        <t>The sender MUST set reserved values to 0.</t>

        <t>Future edition of this specification can specify other values such
        that these values can be ignored by receivers that conform to this
        specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-sender-ext">
        <name>Extension values</name>
        <t>A sender MUST NOT use an extension value.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-send-block-caching">
        <name>Code-block caching</name>

        <t>This section applies only if <tt>C</tt> = 1.</t>

        <t>A sender can improve bandwidth efficiency by only occasionally
        transmitting code-blocks corresponding to static portions of the video
        and otherwise transmitting empty code-blocks. When <tt>C</tt> = 1, and
        as described at <xref target="sec-rcv-block-caching"/>, a receiver
        maintains a simple cache of previously received code-blocks, which it
        uses to replace empty code-blocks.</t>

        <t>A sender alone determines which and when code-blocks are replaced
        with empty code-blocks.</t>

        <t>The sender cannot however determine with certainty the state of the
        receiver's cache: some code-blocks might have been lost in transit, the
        sender doesn't know exactly when the receiver started processing the
        stream, etc.</t>

        <t>A code-block is <em>empty</em> if:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>it does not contribute code-bytes as specified in the parent JPEG
          2000 packet header; or</li>
          <li>if the code-block conforms to <xref target="jpeg2000-15"/>,
          contains an HT cleanup segment and the first two bytes of the Magsgn
          byte-stream are between <tt>0xFF80</tt> and <tt>0xFF8F</tt>.</li>
        </ul>

        <t>NOTE: the last condition allows the encoder to insert padding bytes
        to achieve a constant bit rate even when a code-block does not
        contribute code-bytes, as suggested at <xref target="jpeg2000-15"/>,
        F.4.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-receiver">
      <name>Receiver</name>

      <section anchor="sec-recv-ptstamp">
        <name>PTSTAMP</name>

        <t>Receivers can use <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> values to accelerate sender clock
        recovery since <tt>PTSTAMP</tt> typically updates more regularly than
        <tt>timestamp</tt>.</t>

      </section>

      <section>
        <name>QUAL</name>

        <t>A receiver can discard packets where <tt>QUAL</tt> &gt; N if it is
        interested in reconstructing an image that only incorporates quality
        layers N and below.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="recv-RES">
        <name>RES</name>

        <t>The JPEG 2000 coding process decomposes an image using a sequence of
        discrete wavelet transforms (DWT) stages.</t>

        <table anchor="t-res-ll-example">
          <name>Optional discarding of Body Packets based on the value of the
          <tt>RES</tt> field when decoding a reduced resolution image, in the
          case where N<sub>L</sub> = 5 and all DWT stages consist of both
          horizontal and vertical transforms. The image has nominal width and
          height of W x H.</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Decomposition level</th>
              <th>Resolution level</th>
              <th>Subbands</th>
              <th>Keep all Body Packets with RES equal to or less than this
              value...</th>
              <th>... to decode an image with at most these dimensions</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>HL1,LH1,HH1</td>
              <td>7</td>
              <td>W x H</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>HL2,LH2,HH2</td>
              <td>6</td>
              <td>(W/2) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>HL3,LH3,HH3</td>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>(W/4) x (H/4)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>HL4,LH4,HH4</td>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>(W/8) x (H/8)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>HL5,LH5,HH5</td>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>(W/16) x (H/16)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>0</td>
              <td>LL5</td>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>(W/32) x (H/32)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <t><xref target="t-res-ll-example"/> illustrates the case where each DWT
        stage consists of both horizontal and vertical transforms, which is the
        only mode supported in <xref target="jpeg2000-1"/>. The first stage
        transforms the image into (i) the image at half-resolution (LL1
        sub-bands) and (ii) residual high-frequency data (HH1, LH1, HL1
        sub-bands). The second stage transforms the image at half-resolution
        (LL1 sub-bands) into the image at quarter resolution (LL2 sub-bands) and
        residual high-frequency data (HH2, LH2, HL2 sub-bands). This process is
        repeated N<sub>L</sub> times, where N<sub>L</sub> is the number of
        decomposition levels as defined in the COD and COC marker segments of
        the codestream.</t>

        <t>The decoding process reconstructs the image by reversing the coding
        process, starting with the lowest resolution image stored in the
        codestream (LL<sub>N<sub>L</sub></sub>).</t>

        <t>As a result, it is possible to reconstruct a lower resolution of the
        image by stopping the decoding process at a selected stage. For example,
        in order to reconstruct the image at quarter resolution (LL2), only
        sub-bands with index greater than 2, e.g., HL3, LH3, HH3, HL4, LH4, HH4,
        etc., are necessary. In other words, a receiver that wishes to
        reconstruct an image at quarter resolution could discard all packets
        where <tt>RES</tt> &gt;= 6 since those packets can only contribute to
        HL1, LH1, HH1, HL2, LH2 and HH2 sub-bands.</t>

        <t>In the case where all DWT stages consist of both horizontal and
        vertical transforms, the maximum decodable resolution is reduced by a
        factor of 2<sup>7 - N</sup> if all Body Packets where <tt>RES</tt> &gt;
        N are discarded.</t>

        <table anchor="t-res-lx-example">
          <name>Optional discarding of Body Packets based on the value of the
          <tt>RES</tt> field when decoding a reduced resolution image, in the
          case where N<sub>L</sub> = 5 and some DWT stages consist of only
          horizontal transforms. The image has nominal width and height of W x
          H.</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Decomposition level</th>
              <th>Resolution level</th>
              <th>Subbands</th>
              <th>Keep all Body Packets with RES equal to or less than this
              value...</th>
              <th>... to decode an image with at most these dimensions</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>HL1,LH1,HH1</td>
              <td>7</td>
              <td>W x H</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>HL2,LH2,HH2</td>
              <td>6</td>
              <td>(W/2) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>HX3</td>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>(W/4) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>HX4</td>
              <td>4</td>
              <td>(W/8) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>1</td>
              <td>HX5</td>
              <td>3</td>
              <td>(W/16) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>5</td>
              <td>0</td>
              <td>LX5</td>
              <td>2</td>
              <td>(W/32) x (H/2)</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <t><xref target="t-res-lx-example"/> illustrates the case where some of
        DWT stage consist of only horizontal transforms, as specified at Annex F
        of <xref target="jpeg2000-2"/>.</t>

        <t>A receiver can therefore discard all Body Packets where <tt>RES</tt> is
        greater than some threshold value if it is interested in decoding an
        image with its resolution reduced by a factor determined by the
        threshold value, as illustrated in <xref target="t-res-ll-example"/> and
        <xref target="t-res-lx-example"/>.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-receiver-xtrab">
        <name>Extra information</name>
        <t>The receiver MUST accept values <tt>XTRAC</tt> other than 0 and MUST
        ignore the value of <tt>XTRAB</tt>, whose length is given by
        <tt>XTRAC</tt>.</t>

        <t>Future edition of this specification can specify <tt>XTRAB</tt>
        contents such that this content can be ignored by receivers that conform
        to this specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-receiver-reserved">
        <name>Reserved values</name>
        <t>The receiver MUST ignore the value of reserved values.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-receiver-ext">
        <name>Extension values</name>
        <t>The receiver MUST discard an RTP packet that contains any extension
        value.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-rcv-block-caching">
        <name>Code-block caching</name>

        <t>This section applies only if <tt>C</tt> = 1.</t>

        <t>When <tt>C</tt> = 1, and as specified in <xref
        target="sec-send-block-caching"/>, the sender can improve bandwidth
        efficiency by only occasionally transmitting code-blocks corresponding
        to static portions of the video and otherwise transmitting empty
        code-blocks, as defined at <xref target="sec-send-block-caching"/>.</t>

        <t>When decoding a codestream, and for each code-block in the
        codestream:</t>

        <ul>
          <li>
            if the code-block in the codestream is empty, the receiver MUST
            replace it with a matching code-block from the cache, if one exists;
            or
          </li>
          <li>
            if the code-block in the codestream is not empty, the receiver MUST
            replace any matching code-block from the cache with the code-block
            in the codestream.
          </li>
        </ul>

        <t>Two code-blocks are <em>matching</em> if the following
        characteristics are identical for both: spatial coordinates, resolution
        level, component, sub-band and value of the <tt>TP</tt> field of the
        parent RTP packet.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-media-type">
      <name>Media Type</name>

      <section>
        <name>General</name>

        <t>This RTP payload format is identified using the media type defined at
        <xref target="sec-media-type-def"/>, which is registered in accordance
        with <xref target="RFC4855"/> and using the template of <xref
        target="RFC6838"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-media-type-def">
        <name>Definition</name>

        <dl newline="true">
          <dt>Type name</dt>
          <dd>video</dd>

          <dt>Subtype name</dt>
          <dd>jpeg2000-scl</dd>

          <dt>Required parameters</dt>
          <dd>None</dd>

          <dt>Optional parameters</dt>
          <dd>
            <dl newline="true">
              <dt><tt>pixel</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Specifies the pixel format used by the video sequence.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST be a <tt>URI-reference</tt> as specified in
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is a <tt>relative-ref</tt> as specified in
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>, then it MUST be equal to one of the
                pixel formats specified in <xref target="t-pix-fmts"/> and the
                RTP header and payload MUST conform with the characteristics of
                that pixel format.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not a <tt>relative-ref</tt>, the
                specification of the pixel format is left to the application that
                defined the URI.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, the pixel format is
                unspecified.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt><tt>sample</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Specifies the format of the samples in each component of the
                codestream.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST be a <tt>URI-reference</tt> as specified in
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is a <tt>relative-ref</tt> as specified in
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>, then it MUST be equal to one of the
                formats specified in <xref target="sec-sample-fmts"/> and the
                stream MUST conform with the characteristics of that format.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not a <tt>relative-ref</tt>, the
                specification of the sample format is left to the application that
                defined the URI.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, the sample format is
                unspecified.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt><tt>width</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Maximum width in pixels of each image. Integer between 0 and
                4,294,967,295.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST be a sequence of 1 or more digits.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, the maximum width is
                unspecified.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt><tt>height</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Maximum height in pixels of each image. Integer between 0 and
                4,294,967,295.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST be a sequence of 1 or more digits.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, the maximum height is
                unspecified.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt>signal</dt>
              <dd>
                <t>Specifies the sequence of image types.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST be a <tt>URI-reference</tt> as specified
                in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is a <tt>relative-ref</tt> as specified in
                <xref target="RFC3986"/>, then it MUST be equal to one of the
                signal formats specified in <xref target="sec-signal-fmts"/> and
                the image sequence MUST conform to that signal format.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not a <tt>relative-ref</tt>, the
                specification of the pixel format is left to the application
                that defined the URI.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, the stream consists of an
                arbitrary sequence of image types.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt><tt>caps</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The parameters contains a list of sets of constraints to
                which the stream conforms, with each set of constraints
                identified using an <tt>absolute-URI</tt> defined by an
                application.</t>

                <t>The parameter MUST conform to the <tt>uri-list</tt> syntax
                expressed using ABNF (<xref target="RFC5234"/>):</t> 
                <sourcecode type="abnf">
  uri-list = absolute-URI *(";" absolute-URI)
                </sourcecode>

                <t>Each <tt>absolute-URI</tt> MUST NOT contain any <tt>";"</tt>
                character.</t>

                <t>The application that defines the <tt>absolute-URI</tt> MUST
                associate it with a set of constraints to which the stream
                conforms. Such constraints can, for example, include the maximum
                height and width of images.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, constraints, beyond those
                specified in this document, are unspecified.</t>
              </dd>

              <dt anchor="dt-tile"><tt>tile</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The parameter MUST conform to the <tt>tile</tt> syntax
                expressed using ABNF (<xref target="RFC5234"/>):</t>
                <sourcecode type="abnf">
<![CDATA[
tile        = tile-index "&" image-siz
tile-index  = %x31-39 *%x30-39
image-siz   = 1*HEXDIG
]]>
                </sourcecode>

                <t>If the <tt>tile</tt> parameter is present, each image MUST
                correspond to one tile of a multi-tile image, as defined in
                <xref target="sec-mt-images"/>.</t>

                <t><tt>tile-index</tt> is the index of the tile in the
                multi-tile image.</t>

                <t><tt>image-siz</tt> contains the <tt>SIZ</tt> marker segment
                parameters of the multi-tile image, encoded as a case
                insensitive hexadecimal string.</t>

                <t>The <tt>SIZ</tt> parameters of each single-tile image MUST
                conform to the following:</t>

                <ul>
                  <li><tt>Xsiz</tt> MUST be equal to the smaller of (i) the
                  coordinate of the right edge of tile index
                  <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile image and (ii)
                  <tt>Xsiz</tt> of the multi-tile image.</li>

                  <li><tt>Ysiz</tt> MUST be equal to the smaller of (i) the
                  coordinate of the bottom edge of tile index
                  <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile image and (ii)
                  <tt>Ysiz</tt> of the multi-tile image.</li>

                  <li><tt>XOsiz</tt> MUST be equal to the larger of (i) the
                  coordinate of the left edge of tile index
                  <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile image and (ii)
                  <tt>XOsiz</tt> of the multi-tile image.</li>

                  <li><tt>YOsiz</tt> MUST be equal to the larger of (i) the
                  coordinate of the top edge of tile index
                  <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile image and (ii)
                  <tt>YOsiz</tt> of the multi-tile image.</li>

                  <li><tt>XTOsiz</tt> MUST be equal to the coordinate of the
                  left edge of tile index <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile
                  image.</li>

                  <li><tt>YTOsiz</tt> MUST be equal to the coordinate of the top
                  edge of tile index <tt>tile-index</tt> in the multi-tile
                  image.</li>

                  <li>All other parameters MUST be equal to that in the
                  multi-tile image.</li>
                </ul>

                <t><xref target="fig-multi-tile-diagram"/> illustrates an
                example where a multi-tile image that consists of two tiles is
                transmitted as two single-tile images (images 1 and 2). <xref
                target="fig-multi-tile-parameter-example"/> and <xref
                target="t-mt-example"/> describe the <tt>tile</tt> and
                <tt>SIZ</tt> parameter values, respectively.</t>

                <figure anchor="fig-multi-tile-diagram">
                  <name>Ssiz parameters for a multi-tile image and two
                  corresponding single-tile images 1 and 2.</name>
                  <artwork type="ascii-art">
<![CDATA[
(a) Multi-tile image

<----------Xsiz---------->
<----> XTOSiz
+------------------------+
|    <---Xtsiz---->      |
|    xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
|    x T0         x T1   |     x
|    x     #######x#######     x
|    x     #......x......#     x
|    x     #......x......#     x
+----xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
<---XOsiz-->

(b) Single-tile image 1

<-------Xsiz------>     +--+
<----> XTOSiz           |  | Reference grid
+-----------------+     +--+
|    <---Xtsiz---->
|    xxxxxxxxxxxxxx     xxxx
|    x T0         x     x  x Tile area
|    x     #######x     xxxx
|    x     #......x
|    x     #......x     ####
+----xxxxxxxxxxxxxx     #..# Image area
<---XOsiz-->            ####

(a) Single-tile image 2

<----------Xsiz---------->
<-----XTOSiz------>
+------------------------+
|                        |
|                 xxxxxxxxxxxxx
|                 x T0   |    x
|                 x#######    x
|                 x......#    x
|                 x......#    x
+-----------------xxxxxxxxxxxxx
<-------XOsiz-----X---Xtsiz--->
]]>
                  </artwork>
                </figure>

                <figure anchor="fig-multi-tile-parameter-example">
                  <name>Example <tt>tile</tt> parameter for a multi-tile image that consists of two tiles.</name>
                  <artwork type="ascii-art">
NOTE: '\' line wrapping per RFC 8792

tile=0&amp;00000190000000c8000000c800000000000000\
c8000000c800000064000000000001080000
                  </artwork>
                </figure>

                <table anchor="t-mt-example">
                  <name>Selected <tt>SIZ</tt> parameters for a two-tile image
                  and two corresponding single-time images.</name>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th><tt>SIZ</tt> parameter</th>
                      <th>Two-tile image</th>
                      <th>Image where <tt>tile-index</tt> = 1</th>
                      <th>Image where <tt>tile-index</tt> = 2</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td>XSiz</td>
                      <td>400</td>
                      <td>300</td>
                      <td>400</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>YSiz</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>XTSiz</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>YTSiz</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>XOSiz</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>200</td>
                      <td>300</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>YOSiz</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>XTOSiz</td>
                      <td>100</td>
                      <td>100</td>
                      <td>300</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>YTOSiz</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                      <td>0</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>

              </dd>

              <dt><tt>cache</tt></dt>
              <dd>
                <t>The value of the parameter MUST be either <tt>false</tt> or
                <tt>true</tt>.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is <tt>true</tt>, the field <tt>C</tt> MAY
                be 0 or 1; otherwise the field <tt>C</tt> MUST be 0.</t>

                <t>If the parameter is not specified, then the parameter is
                equal to <tt>false</tt>.</t>
              </dd>
            </dl>
          </dd>

          <dt>Encoding considerations</dt>
          <dd>This media type is framed and binary, see <xref target="RFC6838"
          section="4.8"/>.</dd>

          <dt>Security considerations</dt>
          <dd>See <xref target="sec-sec"/>.</dd>

          <dt>Interoperability considerations</dt>
          <dd>The RTP stream is a sequence of JPEG 2000 images. An
          implementation that conforms to the family of JPEG 2000 standards can
          decode and attempt to display each image.</dd>

          <dt>Published specification</dt>
          <dd>This document</dd>

          <dt>Applications that use this media type</dt>
          <dd>video streaming and communication</dd>

          <dt>Person and email address to contact for further information</dt>
          <dd>Pierre-Anthony Lemieux &lt;pal@sandflow.com&gt;</dd>

          <dt>Intended usage</dt>
          <dd>COMMON</dd>

          <dt>Restrictions on Usage</dt>
          <dd>This media type depends on RTP framing, and hence is only defined
          for use with RTP as specified at <xref target="RFC3550"/>. Transport
          within other framing protocols is not defined at the time.</dd>

          <dt>Author</dt>
          <dd><eref target="mailto:pal@sandflow.com">Pierre-Anthony Lemieux
          </eref></dd>

          <dt>Change controller</dt>
          <dd>IETF Audio/Video Transport Core Maintenance Working Group
          delegated from the IESG.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-sdp">
      <name>Mapping to the Session Description Protocol (SDP)</name>
      <t>The mapping of the payload format media type and its parameters to
      SDP, as specified in <xref target="RFC8866"/> MUST be done according to
      <xref target="RFC4855" section="3"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-iana">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
        <t>This memo requests that IANA registers the content type specified at
        <xref target="sec-media-type"/>.  The media type is also requested to be
        added to the IANA registry for <eref
        target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/rtp-parameters">RTP Payload
        Format MIME types</eref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-sec">
      <name>Security considerations</name>

      <t>RTP packets using the payload format specified in this document are
      subject to the security considerations discussed in <xref
      target="RFC3550"/> , and in any applicable RTP profile such as <xref
      target="RFC3551"/>, <xref target="RFC4585"/>, <xref target="RFC3711"/>,
      <xref target="RFC5124"/>.  However, as <xref target="RFC7202"/> discusses,
      it is not an RTP payload format's responsibility to discuss or mandate
      what solutions are used to meet the basic security goals like
      confidentiality, integrity, and source authenticity for RTP in general.
      This responsibility lays on anyone using RTP in an application. They can
      find guidance on available security mechanisms and important
      considerations in <xref target="RFC7201"/>. Applications SHOULD use one or
      more appropriate strong security mechanisms.  The rest of this Security
      Considerations section discusses the security impacting properties of the
      payload format itself.</t>

      <t>This RTP payload format and its media decoder do not exhibit any
      significant non-uniformity in the receiver-side computational complexity
      for RTP Packet processing, and thus are unlikely to pose a
      denial-of-service threat due to the receipt of pathological data. Nor does
      the RTP payload format contain any active content.</t>

      <t>Security considerations related to the JPEG 2000 codestream contained
      in the payload are discussed at <xref target="RFC3745" section="3"/>.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <reference anchor="jpeg2000-1">
          <front>
            <title abbrev="Rec. ITU-T T.800">Recommendation ITU-T T.800, JPEG
            2000 image coding system: Core coding system</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="06"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="jpeg2000-2">
          <front>
            <title abbrev="Rec. ITU-T T.801">Recommendation ITU-T T.801, JPEG
            2000 image coding system: Extensions</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2021" month="06"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="jpeg2000-15">
          <front>
            <title abbrev="Rec. ITU-T T.814">Recommendation ITU-T T.814, JPEG
            2000 image coding system: High-throughput JPEG 2000</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ITU-T</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019" month="06"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        <reference anchor="rec-itu-t-h273">
            <front>
              <title abbrev="Rec. ITU-T H.273">Recommendation ITU-T H.273,
              Coding-independent code points for video signal type
              identification</title>
              <author>
                <organization>ITU-T</organization>
              </author>
              <date year="2021" month="07"/>
            </front>
          </reference>
          <reference anchor="jpeg2000-9">
            <front>
              <title abbrev="Rec. ITU-T T.808">JPEG 2000 image coding system:
              Interactivity tools, APIs and protocols</title>
              <author>
                <organization>ITU-T</organization>
              </author>
              <date year="2005" month="01"/>
            </front>
          </reference>
          <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8866.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4855.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5371.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4175.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6838.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3551.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4585.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5124.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7201.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7202.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3745.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.5450.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section anchor="sec-pixel-fmts">
      <name>Pixel formats</name>

      <t><xref target="t-pix-fmts"/> defines pixel formats.</t>
      <table anchor="t-pix-fmts">
        <name>Defined pixel formats</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>NAME</th>
            <th>SAMP</th>
            <th>COMPS</th>
            <th>TRANS</th>
            <th>PRIMS</th>
            <th>MAT</th>
            <th>VFR</th>
            <th>Mapping in <xref target="t-color-map"/></th>
          </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>rgb444sdr</td>
            <td>4:4:4</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0, 1</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>rgb444wcg</td>
            <td>4:4:4</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0, 1</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>rgb444pq</td>
            <td>4:4:4</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
            <td>16</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0, 1</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>rgb444hlg</td>
            <td>4:4:4</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
            <td>18</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>0, 1</td>
            <td>RGB</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>ycbcr420sdr</td>
            <td>4:2:0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>ycbcr422sdr</td>
            <td>4:2:2</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>ycbcr422wcg</td>
            <td>4:2:2</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
            <td>1</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>ycbcr422pq</td>
            <td>4:2:2</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
            <td>16</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>ycbcr422hlg</td>
            <td>4:2:2</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
            <td>18</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>9</td>
            <td>0</td>
            <td>YCbCr</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

      <t>Each pixel format is characterized by the following:</t>
      <dl newline="true">
        <dt><tt>NAME</tt></dt>
        <dd>Identifies the pixel format</dd>
        <dt><tt>COMPS</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <dl>
            <dt>RGB</dt>
            <dd>Each codestream contains exactly three components, associated
            with the R, G and B color channels, in order.</dd>
            <dt>YCbCr</dt>
            <dd>Each codestream contains exactly three components, associated
            with the Y, C<sub>b</sub> and C<sub>r</sub> color channels, in
            order.</dd>
          </dl>
        </dd>
        <dt><tt>SAMP</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <dl>
            <dt>4:2:0</dt>
            <dd>The C<sub>b</sub> and C<sub>r</sub> color channels are
            subsampled horizontally and vertically by 1/2.</dd>
            <dt>4:2:2</dt>
            <dd>The C<sub>b</sub> and C<sub>r</sub> color channels are
            subsampled horizontally by 1/2.</dd>
            <dt>4:4:4</dt>
            <dd>No color channels are sub-sampled.</dd>
          </dl>
        </dd>
        <dt><tt>TRANS</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <t>Identifies the transfer characteristics allowed by the pixel
          format, as defined at <xref target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></t>
        </dd>
        <dt><tt>PRIMS</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <t>Identifies the color primaries allowed by the pixel
          format, as defined at <xref target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></t>
        </dd>
        <dt><tt>MAT</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <t>Identifies the matrix coefficients allowed by the pixel
          format, as defined at <xref target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></t>
        </dd>
        <dt><tt>VFR</tt></dt>
        <dd>
          <t>Allows values of the VideoFullRangeFlag defined at <xref target="rec-itu-t-h273"/></t>
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-signal-fmts">
      <name>Signal formats</name>
      <dl newline="true">
        <dt><tt>prog</tt></dt>
        <dd>The stream MUST only consist of a sequence of progressive
        frames.</dd>

        <dt><tt>psf</tt></dt>
        <dd>Progressive segmented frame (PsF) stream. The stream MUST only
        consist of an alternating sequence of first segment and second
        segment.</dd>

        <dt><tt>tff</tt></dt>
        <dd>Interlaced stream. The stream MUST only consist of an alternating
        sequence of first field and second field, where the first line of the
        first field is the first line of the frame.</dd>

        <dt><tt>bff</tt></dt>
        <dd>Interlaced stream. The stream MUST only consist of an alternating
        sequence of first field and second field, where the first line of the
        first field is the second line of the frame.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-sample-fmts">
      <name>Sample formats</name>
      <dl newline="true">
        <dt><tt>8</tt></dt>
        <dd>All components consist of unsigned 8-bit integer samples.</dd>
        <dt><tt>10</tt></dt>
        <dd>All components consist of unsigned 10-bit integer samples.</dd>
        <dt><tt>12</tt></dt>
        <dd>All components consist of unsigned 12-bit integer samples.</dd>
        <dt><tt>16</tt></dt>
        <dd>All components consist of unsigned 16-bit integer samples.</dd>
      </dl>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-summary-of-changes">
      <name>Summary of Changes (Informative)</name>

      <section anchor="sec-summary-of-changes-intro">
        <name>Introduction</name>
        <t>This Appendix summarizes substantive changes across revisions of this
        specification. This summary is informative and not intended to be
        exhaustive.</t>
      </section>

			<section anchor="sec-soc-draft-ietf-avtcore-rtp-j2k-scl-01">
				<name>Changes from <tt>draft-ietf-avtcore-rtp-j2k-scl-01</tt></name>

        <ul>
          <li>Allow multi-tile images in a single stream, in addition to
          allowing multi-tile images to be transmitted as multiple single-tile
          streams, as specified at <xref target="sec-mt-images"></xref>.</li>
          <li>Fix incorrect <tt>TRANS</tt> values at <xref
          target="t-pix-fmts"></xref>.</li>
        </ul>
			</section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
